by your logic we freed ourselves from the
по твоей логике мы освободились из-под
Mongol influence with the arrival of Lenin No no no
монгольского влияния приходом Ленина Нет
yes no I'll explain to you
нет нет да нет я тебе я тебе объясню В
What's the point you've never freed yourself
чём суть вы никогда не освобождались и
from the Tatar-Mongol influence Yes you
от татаро-монгольского влияния Да вы и
are you are part of the Tatar-Mongol
есть вы и есть часть татаро-монгольского
empire
империи
yes oh we
да
once communicated Yes yes we
о когда-то общались помню Да да мы не
communicated more than once Well we communicated several times we communicated
раз общались Ну несколько раз общались
in detail we didn't quarrel I remember
предметно общались не ссорились Я помню
Yes and what what about Zelensky you say what
Да а что что по зеленскому скажете что
about Zelensky say president of Ukraine
по зеленскому говори президент Украины
Well that's what happened with Trump Trump let's
Ну вот что было с трампом
say Trump is not but Trump
Трамп скажем так Трамп не но Трамп
is acting now in relation to
поступает сейчас по по отношению к
Europe Yes and in relation to Ukraine well
Европе Да и по отношению к Украине ну
Ukraine is part of Europe Yeah I see and
Украина - это часть Европы Ага понятно а
Russia Russia without these without any is not
Россия Россия без этих без всяких не
part of Europe no Russia is not part of Europe
часть Европы нет Россия не часть Европы
By what principle is Ukraine part of
По какому принципу Украина - это часть
Europe and Russia no Ukraine
Европы а Россия нет Украина полностью
is completely in the European part yes Russia is
находится в европейской части да Россия
a piece in Russia where territorially it is
кусочком в Россия где территориально в
mainly located Well territorially
основном расположена Ну территориально
Russia is located at least in the east But
Россия расположена хоть на востоке Но
what Moscow what to again come on come on
что Москва что ко ещё раз давай так
take the territory of ROSI  a large
давай так возьми территория РОСИ большая
territory of the Russian Federation lies in
территория Российской Федерации лежит в
Europe or in Asia No, I agree that a
Европе или в Азии Нет я согласен что
large territory lies in Asia as well
большая территория лежит в Азии также
as Turkey, look, there is a piece through we
как Турция смотри кусочек есть чере мы
can Well,
можем Ну а
culturally, culturally, culturally, Russia is
культурно культурно культурно Россия
definitely European ST is not European,
точно европейско СТ не европейская
look, culturally, uh, make Russia European
смотри культурно э Россию сделать
or obv Yes, Peter I wanted to,
европейской или обв её Да захотел Пётр I
here is Peter I, look Wait, no, look, Peter I
вот Пётр I смотри Подожди нет смотри
Peter I really tried to make
Пётр I Пётр I реально пробовал сделать
Russia
Россию
uh European, it was not European and did
ээ европейской она не была европейской и
not become European
не стала европейской
then
тогда
Russia Tatar, Turkic,
Россия Татарская тюркская
all sorts of things, just with the Slavic language
всякая просто со славянским языком
which Orthodoxy was brought from Kyiv, yes And
который православие принесено с Киева да
so Russia is the
А так Россия - это
Horde, so And at what point did Ukraine
Орда так А в какой момент тогда Украина
become
стала
European since the time of
европейской со врем со времён Киевской
Kievan Rus Yeah So
Ага Так Киевской Руси подчинялся
Novgorod and
Новгород и
Novgorod were subordinate to Kievan Rus Yes, Novgorod, look, Novgorod
Новгород Да Новгород смотри Новгород к
has nothing to do with modern Russia The
современной России не имеет никакого
Novgorod Republic In
отношения Новгородская республика В
what year
каком В каком году Новгородская
was the Novgorod Republic Novgorod left
республика была Новгород вышел из Нет
No, no, just look In what century was the
нет нет как раз смотри В каком столетии
Novgorod Republic captured by
Новгородскую Республику захватила
Moscow Well, to me  it seems the fourteenth century
Москва Ну мне кажется век четырнадцатый
fifteenth not the fourteenth later well
пятнадцатый не четырнадцатый позже ну
fifteenth maybe even the sixteenth
пятнадцатый может даже и шестнадцатый
now let's see well yes
сейчас посмотрим ну да
and what follows from this for us in general dates
и что из этого следует нам в целом даты
15th century Yes 10th century that is look this
15 век Да X век то есть смотри вот эта
Horde yes Moscow in the 15th century it was still the
Орда да Москва в XV веке это ещё была
Horde definitely the Horde Yes the prince in Moscow and the
Орда точно Орда Да князь в Москве и
prince in Novgorod they were brothers in
князь в Новгороде они братья были по
fact there again again look where
факту там ещё раз ещё раз смотри где там
who could sit which prince yes this is generally
кто какой князь мог сидеть да это вообще
all in Novgorod Yes ethnically was completely
всё в Новгород Да этнически был совсем
different in the book another prince Side look
другой в кни ещё один княз Сиде смотри
look stop again in Novgorod there lived a
смотри стоп ещё раз в Новгород там жило
Slavic tribe Novgorod Slovenes in
Славянское племя Новгородские словене в
Moscow were not Slavic tribes Moscow
Москве не славянские племена были Москва
is not a Slavic city yes Moscow
- это не Славянский город да Москва -
is Finno-Ugric and Turkic peoples
это фино угорские и тюркские народы там
lived there Well really that is uh the Moscow
жили Ну реально то есть э Московское
principality when it captured the
княжество когда захватило ф угорские
fugrians - it is not Europe Finno-Ugric
народ - это не Европа фино угорский
European part European part not
европейски часть Европейский часть не
European that is Moscow is part of Europe
Европейский то есть Москва часть Европы
Well initially long ago No no no
Ну изначально дав быва Нет нет нет
look  The thing is that
смотри Дело в том что там жили
European people lived there, yes, some
европейские народ жи жили да некоторые И
lived there. But the main backbone of the Russian
жили Но основной Костяк российской
statehood was made up of Turks and
государственности составили тюрки и
Mongols, Tatars, Mongols, and that is to say, after all,
монголы татары монголы а то есть
Turks were everywhere. Yes,
всё-таки тюрки везде были да Ну да
look, come on. So look, they were
посмотри давай давай Так посмотри все их
n’t in Kyiv, they weren’t in Kyiv, all of them were of
не было в Киеве нет в Киеве все эти были
Russian origin, you
русского происхождения Славянского у вас
all had Slavic origin, look, in the Moscow Principality. And so
все смотри в Московском княжестве И так
on. All of these boyar families were
дальше все эти боярские роды это были
Tatars. Yes, for example, what does the
татары Да например там вот что у вас
word Arbat mean in
означает слово Арбат в
Moscow? It’s not clear. Arbaiten may
Москве улица не ясно Арбайтен может быть
not be Arbaiten - it means to work in German. Arbat
не Арбайтен - это работать по неме Арбат
is a Working street. There are all sorts of things there. No, no, no. Well,
- это Рабочая улица там всякие нет нет
what are you telling me? Arbaiten,
нет ну а что ты мне рассказываешь
Arbaiten, it means in German.
Арбайтен вот Арбайтен - это по-немецки
Yes, Arbat. Because when the Germans
да Арбат Потому что когда немцы
came, they settled Arbat. No, where did the
приходили они Арбат заселяли нет Где
Germans settle Arbat.
немцы заселяли
Well, why do you know what’s going on on Arbat? What’s
Арбат Ну а почему Ты знаешь что на
going on there? What’s going on there? Well, it’s a
Арбате вообще происходит Что там Что что
shopping street. That’s
ну это торговая улица правильно вот
right. That’s right. Now you. Why is
правильно Вот теперь ты А почему
Arbat? What is an arba? Yes, tell me.
Арбат Что такое арба Ну да расскажи я
Tell me. What  such an arba You should know
Раскажи Что такое арба Ты должен знаеш
What is an arba I assumed what it is What
Что такое арба я предположил что это
Well what is it from the word arba that
такое Что Ну что это от слова арба что
work not And what is an arba not Arbat And what
рабо не А что такое арба не Арбат А что
is an arba you know or not this I don't
такое арба знаешь или нет это это не
know this in Turkic cart cart they
знаю во это по тюркски повозка повозка
came on carts and from there they traded
приезжали на повозках и оттуда торговали
fairs there were
ярмарки там
Listen I have this kind of a good
были Слушай у меня вот такой вот Хороший
question Look I
вопрос Вот смотри я
looked in Dnepr there is a street Arbat that
посмотрел в Днепре есть улица Арбат то
is Well it turns out I'll
есть Ну получается всё-таки
explain I'll explain The fact is that the
объясню Объясню Дело в том что
Russian Empire Yes
Российская империя Да
impositions on the occupied
навязывания на оккупированных
territories of Ukraine Yes also look in
территориях Украины Да также смотри в
Dnepr there was a street
Днепре была улица
Lenin And before that there were some
Ленина А до этого были какие-то
Alexandrovsky Mikhailovsky in honor of the
александровские Михайловские на честь
tsars Well these are not names and
царей Ну это это не имена и
streets okay No well this is Okay then Well okay
улиц ладно Не ну это Окей тогда Ну
look let's make it very simple Look
хорошо смотри давай очень просто Смотри
when a little ear Just tell me when
когда немного уш Просто скажи когда
Russia When
Россия Когда
Russia became independent from the
Россия стала независимой от
Tatar-Mongols In what
татаро-монгол В каком
year Well there not in the year there in the century And this well
году Ну там не в году там в веке И это
as in the century that this should have
ну как в веке что это должен был
happened at some point that everything from
произойти какой-то момент что вот всё с
this  moment We are independent there there there
этого момента Мы независимы там там там
some Well there in short there also
некоторые Ну там короче там тоже
approximately - 10th century Well as at no no no so no
примерно - X век Ну как при не не не так
No with it did not happen at one moment no no
не Нет с это не в один момент произошло
Look all states became
нет нет Смотри все государства ставали
independent at one moment that is there was a
независимыми в один момент то есть был
moment when some prince there for example
момент когда какой-то князь там например
proclaimed or some people here we
провозгласил или какой-то народ вот мы
can when we became independent for example
можем когда стал независимым например
there from Norman stop Ivan the Terrible He
там от нормандского стоп Иван Грозный Он
when was in the fifteenth or maybe later in
когда был в пятнадцатом или может позже
my opinion in my opinion under Ivan the Terrible
по-моему по-моему при Иване Грозным
actually it all ended yes no well
собственно оно и всё и закончилось
when can you name an event
да нет ну когда можно назвать событие
that like all here declared
которое типа всё вот провозгласили
independence from the Golden Horde
независимость от Золотой Орды
m what conk
м какой конк
well I I don't remember documents now Here here here
ну я я сейчас не помню документы Вот вот
look if we look at the history of any
вот смотри если мы смотрим историю любой
country yes they have there for example
страны да у них есть там например
Portugal became independent there from
Португалия стала независимой там от
France yes Spain was conquered by the
Франции да Испания была завоёвана
Arabs then here At such a moment it was
арабами потом вот В такой момент
freed from the Arabs Yes the Reconquista is
освободилась от арабов Да реконкиста это
clearly there are some moments Yes so the
чётко есть какие-то моменты Да так
question We know for sure yes that the
вопрос Мы точно знаем да что
Tatar-Mongols captured Rus' we know
татаро-монголы захватили Русь мы знаем
when Kyiv was liberated yes exactly here the
когда Киев был освобождён да точно вот
Lithuanian prince  came gave together with the
литовский князь пришёл дал вместе с
Russians our Slavs gave lei to the
русскими ми нашими славянами дали лей
Tatars the Mongols everything is clear Yes
татаро монголам всё чётко есть Да есть
there is a way of life on the blue waters And so on Yes
там быт на синих водах И так дальше Да
all these dates are Yes in Russia and
все есть эти даты Да вот в России и мы
then we became here Kyiv and part of modern
тогда стали вот Киев и часть современной
Ukraine became and Belarus became the Grand
Украины стала и Белорусь стала Великом
Duchy of Lithuania Then it
княжеством литовском Потом она
united with Poland became the
объединилась с Польшей стала речь
Commonwealth Yes and Russia yes When Russia
посполитая Да а Россия да Когда Россия
left yes left the Golden Horde A
вышла да вышла из состава Золотой Орды А
Well let's
Ну давай
[music]
[музыка]
look and Ivan the Terrible is generally the 10th
посмотрим а Иван Грозный это вообще X
century Yes it was
век Да
in
это в
1442 all the princes stopped paying
1442 году все князья перестали платить
tribute accordingly to the Mongol kingdom
Дань соответственно монгольскому царству
stop stop stop in what
стоп стоп стоп в каком а
1472 so this is a lie because
1472 так это брехня потому что ещё
look Peter I paid tribute to the Crimean Khan
смотри ещё Пётр I крымскому хану
Look really look
Дань посмотри вот реально посмотри Дань
Tribute Look you said
Смотри ты сказал
1442 Look for example
1442 Посмотри например
stop because this is a lie Let's
стоп потому что это брехня Давай сейчас
look now when that is we defeated Sweden in the war
смотри когда то есть мы швецию в войне
and the Crimean  khan was
победили а крымскому хану
paid look here for the sake of interest
платили посмотри вот ради интереса
look write
посмотри напиши
Tribute to the Crimean Khan
Дань крымскому хану Вот
Look This is called a funeral service these
посмотри Это называется поминки вот эти
funeral services Yes they were paid to the Crimean
поминки Да выплачивались крымскому
Khanate including the 15th
ханству включая XV
century write Tribute to the Crimean Khanate Yes
век напиши Дань крымскому ханству Да
[music]
[музыка]
Well this is very funny it was not a tribute it was not a
Ну это это очень весело это была не дань
tribute it was compensation for the fact that the Crimean
была не дань это была компенсация за то
Cossacks What Crimean
казаки Какие Крымские
Cossacks you read again about the
казаки ещё раз ты прочитал за
Zaporozhian Cossacks no stop stop what did you
запорожские казаки нет стоп стоп что ты
read again
прочитал ещё раз
read
прочитай
I Read out loud Read tell me where
я Прочитай вслух Прочитай скажи вот где
you look Wikipedia or where somewhere so that
ты смотришь Википедии или где где-нибудь
I can turn off Read out loud
чтобы я откл Прочитай вслух
on
на
Yandex
Яндексе
battle I I I asked Nero now I
сеча я я я у Нерон спросил сейчас я
opened the sources
источники открыл
and
а
pu-pu-pu
пу-пу-пу
and so no well in short In short I don’t know Well
а так не ну короче Короче я не знаю Ну
like with the sources something
типа с источниками что-то это
like
типа
Nero just take it from Google without a
Нерон так просто возьми в Гугле без
neural network take it from Google Yes Peter I Tribute to the
нейронки возьми в Гугле Да Пётр I Дань
Crimean Khanate and you
крымскому ханству и
just want to say that the Russian  the
просто хочешь сказать что Российская
empire that defeated the Swedes was vmo
империя которая победила шведов была вмо
from stop Russian Russian empire is the same
от стоп россий Российская империя этоже
1721 Let's see before the Russian empire,
1721 Давай мы до Российской империи ещё
really,
посмотрим вот реально
look, let's want to say, and historians
посмотри давай хочу сказать а историки
want to say, there are documents,
хотят сказать Документы есть договоры
Peter's treaties, look right now, no, Well, look,
Петра Вот посмотри прямо сейчас нет Ну
look, no, you're running away, no, okay, let's see,
смотри Посмотри Нет ты убегаешь не окей
what will we achieve, you proved to me, you
давай что вот достим ты мне доказал ты
proved that you to me, Doc, let me
доказал что ты мне Дока Давай я тебе
read it to you now, I'll read it, then I'll
сейчас прочитаю я прочита значит
read it to you, then a commemoration, Yes, in the
прочитаю тебе значит поминки Да в
Crimean documents, you are the Treasury, Yes, payments from the
Крымских документах тыж Казна Да выплаты
Russian, this state of yours, to the
русского вот этого вашего государства
Crimean Khanate in the
крымскому ханству в
15th centuries, which had different periods,
15 веках имевшие разные периоды
regular or irregular in nature, were
регулярный или нерегулярный характер Так
paid both in money and in kind, fur,
выплачивались как деньгами так и натурой
walrus tusk, and so on, Yes, what are
меха моржовый клык и так дальше Да что
you proving with this,
ты этим доказываешь
look, let's see, in the 15th century, this custom was not
смотрим в XV веке этот обычай не был
enshrined, the Russian side was such an
закреплён русская сторона так
obstacle to the conclusion, remember, the sixth
препятствие заключени стать помни шесте
charter, we are talking about ne, wait, stop,
грамоты мы о пе говорим подожди стоп
now, I'm reading you the whole chronology,
сейчас так я тебе всю хронологию читаю
Yes, I don't need the whole thing  chronology let's get
Да мне не нужна вся хронология давай
to the point again the point you said in
сразу ещ раз к сути суть ты сказал в в
forty-second the prince stopped paying
сорок втором князя перестали платить
tribute I told you to open it right now
Дань я тебе сказал открой прямо сейчас
you opened it you had a defensive laugh
ты открыл у тебя был защитный смех
Because you saw it and I'm telling you
Потому что ты это увидел и я тебе говорю
look 10th century 100 years after that
смотри X век через 100 лет после этого
yes they pay Yes that's what you said and
да платят Да вот ты про пего сказал и
now we'll get to Peter Look after
сейчас до Петра дойдём Смотри после
double payment here in 1564
двойной выплаты вот 1564 год
yes Moscow was ruined by Davlet Gray Crimean
да Москву разорил Давлет Грей Крымский
Khan Davlet Gray ruined Moscow in
Хан Давлет герей разорил Москву в
1571 1571
1571 1571
it seems 100 years after you
вроде через 100 лет после того как ты
said that they no longer paid tribute look
сказал что уже не платили дать посмотри
it's a fact but you still Well not really
это ж факт но ты ещ Ну не на самом деле
something else happened Yes
что-то было ещё Да
1571 Crimean Khan Okay let's do it like that and
1571 год Крымский Хан Окей давай так а
then the Poles also ruined Moscow
потом ещё и поляки Москву разорили
wait wait wait wait no
подожди подожди подожди подожди нет
Come on now you said that in 1442 they
Давай ты сейчас ты сказал что 1442
stopped paying tribute That's not true like
перестали платить Дань Это неправда вот
that further Further look after the end of the
так дальше Дальше смотри после окончания
Time of Troubles in  In 1615 I read
смутного времени в 1615 году я читаю
the facts the practice of payments to the Crimean Khanate
факты практика выплат крымскому ханству
was fixed by the agreement Since then they
была закреплена договором С тех пор они
were made annually increasing in
производились ежегодно возрастая по
amount Yes, no, you hit the same point here
сумме Да вот нет ты бьёшь в одну точку
Let's see who else the
вот Давай мы посмотрим много кто ещё
Poles then Moscow after that zakh again again again again
поляки потом Москву после этого зах ещё
Look, you caught
раз ещё раз ещё раз Смотри ты ты поймал
you said that I just asked When did
ты сказал что я же спросил просто Когда
you gain independence from the Golden
Вы получили независимость от Золотой
Family What are you doing there Googled and said in
роды Ты что там Погугли и сказал
1442 the prince stopped paying tribute I
1442 году князя перестали платить Дань я
say This is not true one thing is the
говорю Это неправда одно одно дело это
Golden Horde another
Золотая Орда другое
Crimean Khanate is part of the Golden RD
Крымское ханство это часть золотой РД
was this Western wing of the Golden RD yes I
было это Западное крыло золотой РД да
see
Понятно
Okay Yes, study history so on And when did the
Окей Да учи историю так дальше А когда
Golden Horde end When was
закончилась Золотая Орда Когда было
Crimea so Look further further no
Крымское так Смотри дальше дальше нет
stop and when
стоп а когда
was you burning Crimean Khanate
было горишь Крымское ханство
was Here is the whole point
было Вот
in the draft peace treaty of Russia with
в проекте мирного договора России с
Crimea in
Крымом
1692 Yes when was it already Peter I
1692 года Да когда это уже был Пётр I
1692 was Yes no I can't
1692 год был Да нет я я не могу тебя
listen to you as long as you I Peter I I you  about
слушать как пока ты я Пётр I я тебе про
Peter I I say come on PT 1692 was already
Петра I говорю давай ПТ 1692 год был уже
Peter I no Yes come on first and once again
Пётр I нет Да давай так сначала а ещё
you said the Crimean Khanate part
раз ты ты сказал Крымское ханство часть
again Look yes yes Peter I was already Yes
ещё раз Смотри да да Пётр I был уже Да
then look I am officially telling you
значит смотри я тебе официально говорю
Look yes here is 1600 far somewhere 1692 year
Смотри да вот 1600 даль гдето 1692 год
peace treaty of Russia with Crimea with the
мирный договор России с Крымом с
Crimean Khanates Yes there was no Hang out don't run away don't run away don't
Крымских ханств Да была не Зависай не
run away
убегай не убегай не убегай
ran away that's all Yes this laughter of his
убежал вот и всё Да этот вот его смех
was very indicative Yes he What kind of tribute are
был очень показательным Да он Какая Дань
you what and he reads and he is hysterical
ты что и он читает и у него истерика
Just hysterical Yes because Russians
Просто истерика Да потому что россияне
live in a fake history yes Russia
живут в фейковой истории да Россия
never left the Horde Russia
никогда не выходила из Орды Россия и
is part of the Golden Horde Yes part of
есть часть Золотой Орды Да часть вот
this vassal structure Yes simply the
этой ва вассальная структура Да просто
Golden Horde due to its huge
Золотая Орда в силу своего огромного
empire disintegrated into parts the Crimean
империи распалась на части Крымское
Khanate there these northern
ханство там вот эти северные княжества
Tatar principalities there Astrakhan And so on Yes
татарские там Астраханские И так дальше
and then they began
Да и дальше уже начали они друг друга
to absorb each other and Moscow here is the state
поглощать и Московская вот э государство
Yes  paid tribute to the Crimean Khanate in the
Да платило Дань Да крымскому ханству и в
10th century and in there and he at the end of the seventeenth
X веке и в там и он в конце семнадцатого
on here During the Russian-Turkish
на вот Во время русско-турецких
negotiations in 1713 yes in Novo the
переговоров в 1713 году да в Ново возник
question arose about the annual tribute to the Crimea by the Russians
вопрос о ежегодной Дани в Крым русским
so they postponed its discussion to another
так перенесли его обсуждение на другое
time That's all like him I love these
время Вот вот и всё как он Я люблю эти
moments when they open their
моменты когда они открывают свои
historical this and just start w
исторические это и начинают просто ж
Read Don't laugh He has hysterical
Прочитай Не смейся У него истерический
laughter it was divine just oh Where did
смех это было божественно просто о Куда
you run away you come on come on we have it
ты убежал ты давай давай давай мы у меня
open with me open with me Yes you looked
открыто у меня открыто Да ты посмотрел
read No I have it disappeared and in
почитал Нет я у меня это пропали и в
general it's well so Read Come on Take me me me me here
общем-то это ну так Почитай Давай Возьми
in fact
мне мне мне мня вот на самом деле Просто
I would just like to go back a little Here to the
я бы хотел вернуться немножко Вот в
beginning that we went somewhere so here
начало что мы куда-то ушли так вот
Well look at the moment when we went to
Хорошо смотри момент когда мы пошли
sell you said that I asked so when
прода ты сказал что я спросил так когда
Russia gained independence from the Golden
Россия получила независимость от Золотой
became an independent state when
стала независимым государством когда
but come on then I will ask a counter
а вот давай тогда я задам встречный
question
вопрос
a a Is it so
а а Является ли это так
important that there was exactly some
важно чтобы был именно некоторый
document stop look we can Well or an
документ стоп смотри мы можем Ну или
event  some This could not have been a
событие какое-то Вот это не могло быть
century, that is, some turning
столетие то есть какой-то переломный
point, today we are in this state,
момент вот сегодня мы в этом государстве
and tomorrow we are free. For example,
А завтра мы свободны Вот например
look very clearly at the moment when the
очень чётко смотри момент когда
Mongols, the Tatar-Mongols, captured Kyiv. Yes, there
монголы татаро-монголы захватили Киев Да
is a moment. When the Lithuanians liberated
есть момент Когда литовцы освободили
Kyiv. There is a moment when the Lithuanian
Киев Есть момент когда Литовское
state united with the Polish state. There are
государство соединилось там с польским
all these moments. There is a moment when the
есть эти все моменты Есть момент когда
Commonwealth collapsed. Yes, so
распалась реч посполитая есть да Так вот
when Russia became an independent
когда Россия стала независимым
state when it was captured by the Poles,
государством когда её захватили поляки
not when it became an independent
не когда она стала независимым
state. Well, when the Poles captured it,
государством Ну вот когда её захватили
they drove out the Tatars, the Mongols,
поляки они выбили татара монголов
and therefore Russia. It was never
и поэтому Россия Она никогда не была
actually an independent state.
собственно независимым государством она
Well, the Polish Polish kingdom is Russia.
Ну польское польское царство это Россия
That is, when it
То есть когда когда это
was
было
what, well, Minin Pozharsky, this is your
что ну Минин Пожарский это же ваша
history. Well, when it
история Ну когда это
was in the sense. What does Minin and Pozharsky have to do with it?
было в смысле Причём тут Минин и
You don’t know what Minin and
Пожарский ты не знаешь что такие Минин и
Pozharsky are. And who drove out the Poles? What does the
Пожарский А кто Поляков прогонял Причём
Golden Rda have to do with it? What did you say? The Poles
тут золотая рда то что ты сказал поляки
drove out the Golden
прогнали золотую
Arda. So what, the Gazov uprising, who are the
арду Ну и что ну востание газова кто
Menin Pozharskys?  were Well, they
такие Менины пожарские были
organized the Uprising, they expelled the
Ну организовали Восстание изгнали
legitimate Polish Tsar
этих законного царя польского
Well, that is, they made the Maidan
Ну то есть Майдан сделали
Well, ty I mean, what's the difference Well, he was
Ну ти В смысле какая разница Ну он был
not very legitimate, so to speak, I mean, not legitimate,
не очень законным так сказать в смысле
he was legitimate Well,
не законным как раз он был законным Ну
look, they expelled him Yes, if he was, he
смотри его прогнали Да если он был он
captured, accordingly No, that's
захватил соответственно Нет вот именно
exactly it, he didn't capture, he didn't capture Well, when, when they expelled the Polish Tsar, stop, stop, stop, you don't know your history, he didn't capture And what did he do And how did he become king Well, like, you want to say that the boyars
Ну типа ты хочешь сказать что его бояри
put him there Well, yes, yes, and the mines, fire engines,
туда посадили Ну а да да а мины пожарки
corrupted battles, which Note, and corrupt
коррумпированные боя которы Прим причём
And why corrupt Well,
коррумпированный А почему
because
коррумпированный Ну потому что боярам ты
you give the boyars money and that's it No, no, no,
типа ты даёшь денег и всё нет нет нет
look, in those years Yes, it was normal that they
смотри в тех годах Да было нормально что
united just like Lithuania
вот объединялись также как Литва
united Poland It was not beneficial to
объединилась Поль это не было выгодно
most people Why
большей части людей Почему
What kind of
Каких
people Look, these commoners,
людей смотри людей вот этих простолюдина
no one considered them at all, they
вообще никто не считал они
used the Polish Tsar to
были использовали польского царя для
advance their interests Well, like, this
продвижения своих интересов Ну типа это
doesn't say anything about the World Cup  look again
не говорит Ни о ЧМ не смотри ещё раз
then and Rurik who was called to Novgorod at all
значит а Рюрика которого вообще в
let's not
Новгород призвали не давай не
give up the call direction it was
возвращаться призыв направление это была
normal practice
нормальная практика
let me remember but then I'll
Давай я вспомню А вот а вот тогда я
tell you the next one look this it's
скажу тебе следующую Смотри это Это мне
not important to me tell me when Russia
не существенно ты скажи Когда Россия
gained independence this is the year when it
получила независимость вот год когда она
became an independent state well here is
стала независимым государством Ну вот
Russia as which as a state
Россия как которая как государство
that exists now in the ninety-
которое существует сейчас В девяносто
first year in the ninety-first year yes that
первом году В девяносто первом году Да
is until the ninety-first year
всё то есть до девяносто первого года
your state did not exist as did
вашего государства не существовало как и
Ukraine yes as did Ukraine Absolutely right Well I
Украины Да как и Украины Абсолютно верно
agree yes okay good come on if we
Ну согласен да О'кей хоро Давай Если
look at the state that
посмотрим государство которое
existed before 1917 the Russian
существовало до 1917 года Российская
Empire Yes when this state
империя Да когда это государство
appeared when it gained
появилось когда она получила
independence when it became
независимость когда она стала
independent the Russian
самостоятельным Российская
Empire We understand that look Peter I
империя Мы же понимаем что смотри Пётр I
renamed after after the
переименовал после после смутного
Time of Troubles when
времени когда
Mikhail Fedorovich came here he
там Михаил Фёдорович Пришёл вот он
announced together with Romi
объявил вместе с Роми
who he
кого
announced like that well come on I'll see when
объявил так Ну давай Я посмотрю когда
Russia became an empire no it became an empire
Россия стала империей нет Империя она
in 1721
стала в 1721 году
it was asked to be the emperor of all Russia
её просился императором всероссийским
here is 1721 I think that Russia is
вот 1721 год я считаю что Росси
not here Look this is it when it
ипе нет Смотри это она когда она
gained independence Here is this
получила независимость Вот это
state in 1721 there was simply a
государство в 1721 году произошло просто
renaming of the Muscovite kingdom to the
переименование Московского царства в
Russian Empire that is Peter I simply
Российскую империю то есть Пётр I просто
renamed no this
переименовал нет это
would
бы в
mean there were 2 years as it
смысле там там 2 лет как
was there 20 years as St. Petersburg was the capital
было там 20 лет как Питер был столицей
what was it Muscovite kingdom
какое оно Московское царство было ещё
again Well it was a kingdom Well St. Petersburg is the
ещё раз Ну царство это было Ну Питер
capital and what was it called Muscovite
столица а как оно называлось Московское
kingdom with the capital in St. Petersburg yes simply and what was it called
царство со столицей в Питере да просто а
normally good so what was it
как оно называлось нормально хорошо
called when the
давай так как оно называлось когда
capital Let me ask you this It
столицу Давай я это у тебя спрошу Вот
seems to me just you tell me Well there was
мне кажется просто ты скажи Ну было
Muscovite kingdom it was always
Московское царство оно было отродясь
Muscovite kingdom with a face
Московское царство со лицем
Yes now too in fact Muscovy yes
Да сейчас тоже на самом деле Московия да
yes Muscovy Absolutely
да Московия Абсолютно
right This is funny this is good look what it was
верно Вот это весело это хороо смотри
called years
как называлось года
I don't understand m World Cup we are talking now we have they
Я не понимаю м ЧМ мы говорим сейчас у
said that so you run away
нас вот сказали что так ты убегаешь
look we sweat we spent a lot of time
смотри мы пот мы потратили кучу времени
yes And once again we go when this
да И ещё раз ходим когда вот это
state Yes  became independent from the
государство Да стало независимым от
Golden
Золотой
Horde in
Орды в
172 No, this is also a state that
172 Нет это это тоже государство что
was in 1720 It just changed its name
было в 1720 Просто оно сменило название
Okay, I
Окей я тебя
called you Why not, no, well, we I
назвал Почему нет нет ну мы Я же тебе
showed you that in short it was Tribute Then and that's it And
показал что короче было Дань Потом и всё
I, well, those are obligatory liberated from ed that
А я те хорошо те обя освободились изд то
is, according to your logic, we liberated ourselves
есть по твоей логике мы освободились
from the Mongol influence with the arrival of
из-под монгольского влияния приходом
Lenin No, no, I'll explain to you
Ленина Нет нет нет я тебе я тебе объясню
What's the point you never liberated yourself from the
В чём суть вы никогда не освобождались и
Tatar-Mongol influence Yes, you
от татаро-монгольского влияния Да вы и
are you and you are part of the Mongol Empire
есть вы и есть часть монгольской империи
Yes, you are part, you just look I'll
Да вы есть часть вы просто смотри я тебе
explain to you I have seen the light yes look many
объясню я прозрел да посмотри многие В
What's the point many
чём суть многие
Tatar noble families they simply
татарские знатные рода они просто
accepted Christianity Orthodoxy
принимали христианство православие
simply baptized the fact is that look in the
просто крещён дело в том что смотри в
Golden Horde of the times when the Tatars
золотой арде времён когда татары
baptized Yes, I know not yet look
хрестили Да я знаю ещё нет смотри ты
now come on so what was the religion in the
сейчас давай так какая была религия в
Golden Horde when it captured
Золотой Орде когда захвати
Rus' Well, there, there I don't know but it
Русь Ну там там я я не знаю но мне
seems to me there was rather no religion there
кажется там скорее не было религии там
it was
это
Here is Islam yet  there was no golden
было Вот Ислама ещё не было в золотой
rda Yes there was Tengrianism yes there was
рде Да там были тенгрианства да тут было
Orthodoxy there was paganism And so
православие там были язычество И так
on Yes therefore also those Tatars Yes
дальше Да поэтому также те татары Да
Kazan all they were not
казанские всё они ещё не были
Muslims then they were not
мусульманами тогда они не были
Muslims and many Tatars Yes they
мусульманами и многие татары Да они
accepted Orthodoxy here if you look at
принимали православие вот если посмотри
all for example not all because many
все например не все потому что многие
noble families they are German or
дворянские рода они есть немецкие либо
Scottish in the Russian Empire And the
шотландские в Российской империи А
majority are Tatar For example
большинство - это татарские Вот например
take Kutuzov Yeah kutuz o ov - it's
возьми Кутузов Угу кутуз о ов - это
just an ending like now for example
просто окончание вот Как сейчас например
this Kadyr ov Kadyr is a name Yes here a
этот Кадыр ов Кадыр - это имя Да вот а
ov it's just added like Ivanov Yes
ов это просто добавляется как Иванов Да
also Exactly Kutuzov stop a a a here
также Вот именно Кутузов стоп а а а вот
a Budanov - this is also in one network Yes
а Буданов - это тоже в одну сети Да
look Budanov is a surname from buda Yes buda budan
смотри Буданов - это фамилия от буда Да
some kind of yes O that is Budanov
буда будан какой-то да О то есть Буданов
budan of here yes yes some kind of budan It is necessary it is
будан оф вот да да какой-то будан Надо
necessary to look where from where from where no
надо посмотреть откуда откуда откуда нет
Neya What do the Mongols have to do with it I'm telling you that
Нея Причём тут монголы я тебе говорю что
specifically the surname is kutuz Kutuzov from the name
конкретно фамилия кутуз Кутузов от имени
kutuz  Turkic went Yeah, if of, it doesn't
кутуз тюркского пошло Ага если оф это не
mean that of is a Russian ending,
значит что оф - это русское кончание
look at her, and I Pony outside the windows,
смотри её а я Поня вне окон
nishin there, ishin, for example, in Russia, ov
н ишин там ишин например в России ов
was made when they gave surnames, Yes, by names,
делали когда давали фамилии Да по именам
for example, Kadyr ov, yes, tus ov, yes, Ivan ov,
например Кадыр ов да тус ов да Иван ов
here's Ivan ov, Ivan is Russian, I understand what
вот Иван ов Иван - это рус я понял о чём
you're talking about. But there are owls of different languages, like,
ты говоришь А вот бывают сову разных язы
for example, my surname is fakov, well, am
как вот у меня например фамилия факов
I
вот ну я что ли
like, or like fv? I know what kind of surname it is, you need to
типа или как фв Я знаю что за фамилия
look at the etymology, but what I'm
надо посмотреть этимологию но к чему я
getting at is that,
веду что
look, it's important, the majority of Russian
смотри важно большинство российских
noble families are Tatars, Tatars. For
дворянских родов это татары татары Вот
example, these, like them, Tatar
например эти как они вот татарски
mur, what surnames did they have.
мур какие у них фамилии
Well, you
были Ну вот ты
say, the majority are
говоришь большинство
also ti and a bunch of a bunch of others, badger, barsu,
также ти и куча куча других барсук барсу
badger is not a Slavic name,
барсук - это не славянское название вот
look, yusu, look, the Yusupovs, the one who
смотри юсу вот смотри юсуповы вот тот
made the assassination attempt, Yusup, it's from the
что покушение делал Юсуп это ж от
Tatar name Yusup, it's like  analogue of
татарского имени Юсуп это как аналог
Jewish Joseph Yes, this is Yusu, no, Yusup
еврейского Иосиф Да вот это юсу нет у
has Slavic ones,
юсупа есть славянские
like, look, now I'm telling you for sure,
каже посмотри вот сейчас это я точно
I'm Yusuf, this is Joseph, this is Joseph, this is in
я это ж Юсуф это Иосиф это Джозеф это в
different cultures in Europe, this is Joseph, okay, okay, yes, the
разных культурах в Европе Это Джозеф Да
Yusupovs are a
ладно хорошо да то есть юсуповы - это
Tatar family, we found one of all the Yusupovs,
татарский род Все юсуповы мы нашли один
Karamzin, Karamzin, yeah, yeah,
Карамзин
I'm telling you, Look, it's not that I want a
Угу ч я я тебе Смотри я не то что хочу
postbank, look, we'll open it now,
постбанк Вот посмотри Мы сейчас откроем
and there are a lot of them, yes, in those days, there
и их куча есть да в во времена чтобы их
should be a lot of them, Well, more than 100,
было куча их должно быть Ну больше 100
you can find me, 100 now, Yes,
Ты можешь меня вот 100 сейчас нать Да
you haven't had more than 100, 100 families, And
больше 100 у вас не было 100 родов А
now, look, let's talk about the Turkic
сейчас смотри давай тюркские
families, here are the Sheremetyevs, these are also Turks, Yes,
рода вот Шереметьева это тоже тюрки Да
Sheremet most likely, yes,
Шеремет скорее всего да
Sheremet Maybe, I'm not sure
Шеремет Может быть я сейчас не уверен
about Sheremetyev, I'm not sure, I'll
насчёт Шереметьева не уверен сейчас
look now, Yes, the Morozovs are not Morozov, most
посмотрю Да Морозовы не Морозов скорее
likely, Russian,
всего русс
not now, Well, it seems to me, wait a little,
сечас не Ну мне кажется р немножко
No, not
подожди Не не
Met, Who else?  lopukhi
Мет Кто ещё лопухи
lopukhinykh too Look stop stop stop
лопухиных тоже Смотри стоп стоп стоп
Look I typed in Sheremet etymology
Смотри я вот вбил Шеремет этимология
right I would be interested yes the
прямо Вот мне интересно стало бы да
origin of this surname is traced outside the
происхождение этой фамилии на вне
Turkic root is known
прослеживается тюркский кор известн
linguist ecologist
лингвист еколог
ba po sh Yes it is with Chuvash I
ба по ш Да это с чувашским показал Я
just showed it right away and Oksano Belo Solo look
просто сразу а оксано бело соло смотри
look maybe you read somewhere like
смотри может это ты где-то читаешь типа
such uh Belozersky Yes I will explain I will
такие ээ белозерские Да я я объясню
explain look No Belozersky if there
Объясню смотри Нет Белозерский если
were such It is most likely
такие были Это скорее всего
territorial by Beloe Ozero Yes
территориальный по белому озеру Да
because many For example if
потому что многие Вот например если
you look at this Turgenev yes yes here uh
посмотришь этот Тургенев да да вот э
Turgenev he is also like Turkic here is
Тургенев он же тоже типа тюркский вот
Turgen if you look yes And I stop I am telling
турген если ты посмотришь да А я стоп Я
you now I am not I am not with Turkic
тебе сейчас я не я не с тюркская
literature definitely Turgen I understand here
литература точно турген я понял вот
come on so if you here was was trk
давай так если ты вот был был был трком
I
я
Look you are interrupting now on
Посмотри ты сейчас перебиваешь
purpose because you are wrong I will
специально потому что ты не прав Я тебе
explain to you the Turgenev family Yes moved to the
объясню род тургеневых Да переселился на
territory of modern Belarus Yes  here and
территорию современной Белоруси Да вот и
uh Turgenev Yes this is a Turkic name surname
ээ Тургенев Да это имя тюркское фамилия
look No well well I agree So
посмотри Не ну ну я я согласен Так
look Well damn well Sokolov and Sokolov wait a little longer No
посмотри Ну блин ну Соколов а Соколов
look again
подожди ещё Нет посмотри Ещё раз
Look again about Turgenev really
посмотри про Тургенев реально
Well here is Turgeneva Wikipedia Turge Miliya
Ну вот тургеньева Википедия турге милия
Turgenev has ancient roots and is connected with the
Тургенев имеет древние корни и связаны с
history of the Russian nobility it
историей русского дворянства оно
comes from the name of the Turgen River
происходит от названия реки тургень
which flows
которая протекает
right now Tuge Turge noble
вко прямо сечас туге турге дворянские
families of Tatar origin Turge Bon
роды татарского происхождения турге Бон
description believe
описание верить
Wikipedia Open
Википеди Открой сечас ещ
Wikipedia again now just fachi teani
Википеди просто фачи теани
polini father belonged to the impoverished
полини отца принадлежала к обедневшей
Turgeniv family in the Tula aristocracy
роду тургенива в Тульской аристократии
tracing its history back to the 15th century when the
ведущему свою историю с XV века когда
Tatar Murza Lev Turgen after
татарский Мурза Лев турген после
baptism Ivan Turgenev left the Golden
крещения Иван Тургенев покинул золотую
Arda
арду
Read read about again here and
Прочитай прочитай про ещё раз вот а
maybe after all the Turgen River read again here
может всё-таки река тургень ещё раз вот
look if you don't trust
прочитай смотри если ты не доверяешь
Wikipedia take and here yourself on Google Well
Википедии возьми и вот сам на Гугли Ну
here  open open look come on
вот открой открой смотри давай так
look you I read you facts you
смотри ты я тебе читаю факты ты
start to think Come on open and pos
начинаешь до мысля Давай открой и пос
look Come on again not a river gen What kind of
смо Давай ещё раз не река гень Какая
biography do you want look Turgenev's biography
хочешь посмотри биография Тургенева
has long been researched Here take look
давно исследована Вот возьми посмотри
Turgenev's mouth come on take it on Google Oh it's
рот Тургенева давай возьми на Гугле Ой
hard for me everything is clearly written yes
мне тяжело вот всё чётко написано да
like here cro tur genium yes
типа вот кро тур гениум да
when look Tatar Murza Lev Turgen
когда смотри татарский Мурза Лев турген
after baptism and Ivan Turgenev
после крещения и Иван Тургенев просто
they just accepted Orthodoxy and Val not
они принимали православие и вал не
Turgen by the name of Turgen yes like here he is
турген по имени турген да типа вот он
Val Turgenev or there
вал Тургенев или там
Turge look Well I didn't make it up you Well okay Well okay Okay Okay I
турге посмотри Ну я же не придумал ты Ну
found in
окей Ну о'кей О'кей Ладно я я нашёл в
which it was said bo Yes now
котором об этом говорилось бо Да теперь
Lermontov And maybe or maybe Lika Turgen
Лермонтов А может а может Лика тургень
wait Lika Turgen maybe not Well look
подожди Лика тургень может не Ну смотри
You'll make it up now look
Это ты сейчас придумаешь теперь смотри
Lermontov he's Russian Yeah No no definitely
Лермонтов он русский Ага Нет нет точно
no Exactly
нет Точно
Exactly 100% Who is he Who is Fin Fin no
Точно 100% Кто он Кто Фин Фин нет
Scotsman a  Scotsman from the Lermont family
шотландец а шотландец из рода лермон
look from the Lermont family Lermont Lermont I am
посмотри из рода лермон лермон лермон я
by
по
Yes I am from the Lermont family I am an honest person
Да род с род лермон я честному человеку
I can't look I want you to
я не могу посмотри Я хочу чтобы ты сам
check it yourself You are an honest person not I want
проверил Ты честный человек не Я хочу
you to check it yourself I want you to
чтобы ты сам проверил Я хочу чтобы ты
see it with your own eyes take it to Go
Своими глазами это увидел возьми на Go
No I am I am write Lermont is happening I have
Нет я я я я напиши лерма происхо У меня
such a question No I want I want you to
такой вопрос Нет я хочу я хочу чтобы ты
pour it out now please check
это сейчас нагу лил пожалуйста проверь
Well George Lermont okay Yes so that's it
Ну Джордж лермонт окей Да так вот да
look where I'm getting at before the time of Peter I
смотри к чему я веду до времён Петра I
yes before the time of Peter I the main
да до времён Петра I основной как бы
backbone of the Russian this Russian
Костяк русского вот этого Российского
state Yes the Tatars were the
государства Да составляли татары
Tatar murzas the same Here is Turgen
татарские мурзы тот же самый Вот тургене
and so on Just if you dig you
и так дальше Просто если ты копь тебе
first find it funny like Turgenev like
сначала стаёт смешно типа Тургенев типа
what Tatars op
какие татары оп
yes since the time of Peter I when he cut a
да со времён Петра I когда он прорубил
window to Europe Yes so they started to attract
окно в Европу Да вот э начали привлекать
to the Russian Empire uh noble families
в Российскую империю ээ дворянские роды
uh German uh
э немецкого
French then this Prussian
французского потом этого прусского
Scottish and others  origins Yes,
шотландского и других происхождений Да
if we look, yes,
вот если мы посмотрим да
uh, almost all the figures of the Russian Empire
ээ почти все деятели Российской империи
Yes Look there, the Barents Sea, the one who Yes,
Да Посмотри там Баренцево море тот тот
uh, was the Barents Sea Yes Who is
который Да ээ был Баренцево море да Кто
Barintsev, definitely not Barin Barents Barents Bari Bari
такой баринцев точно не Барин
Barin, no, that's
баренц баренц Бари Бари Барин не то это
some German surname Yes Then let's
какая-то немецкая фамилия да Потом давай
look further Elizabeth or Catherine Catherine,
посмотрим дальше Елизавета или Екатерина
she was German, was the queen
Екатерина она ж немка была царица
Catherine Well, yes, she was German, you won't
Екатерина Ну да немка ты не будешь это
deny it, right It will be difficult Yes, yes,
отрицать правда Это будет сложно Да да
there, Olga Tsarskaya or somehow she
там э Ольга Царская или как-то она меня
won't let me speak out That is,
не выговориться Вот то есть
in the Golden Horde Yes, in these principalities Yes,
в золотой Орде Да в этих княжествах Да
which are Moscow and so on, they were all
которые московские и так далее это всё
Tatars, there were Russian Tatars, maybe
татары были татары русские может
they are modern there And they lived somewhere in some
современные они там И жили где-то в
villages Yes, how And the whole reign
сёлах какие-то Да как А всё правление
was Tatars Yes, they were simply baptized and
были татары Да просто они крестились и
became like he was Turgen, yes he became
ставали вот как он был турген да стал
Ivan Turgenev at baptism
при крещении Иван
and now there is a lot of this on the
Тургенев и очень много теперь такое на
helmet of Ivan the Terrible
шлеме Ивана Грозного
Yes, you know that there was Arabic script m  I
Да ты знаешь что была арабская вязь м я
heard that I won't I won't argue with you that
слышал я это я не буду я не буду с тобой
it's not a myth because
спорить о том что это не миф потому что
arguing with you is really not interesting that's
с тобой спорить очм это не интересно вот
why I just agree with you Let's
поэтому я просто с тобой согласен Давай
not do that that is look yes that is you've already
не то то есть смотри да то есть ты уже
taken such a defensive position oh okay
взял такую защитную позицию те о'кей
Okay I agree with you so as not to
О'кей я с тобой согласен чтобы не
argue Yes the question is because it's
спорить Да вопрос а потому что это
pointless I won't prove anything to you now of course you wo
бессмысленно я тебе ничего сейчас не
n't prove it to me because
докажу мне конечно не докажешь потому
I rely on I rely on facts And you the
что я опираюсь я опираюсь на факты А ты
question Why did Prince Ugu yes Ivan
вопрос Почему у князя Угу да Ивана
the Terrible Yes the Slavic prince a had
Грозного Да князя славянина а была
Arabic ligature on his helmet because he was a
арабская вязь на шлём потому что он
Mongol or a Finn I don't
Монгол или Фин Я не
know no Well by the way in general it could be
знаю не Ну кстати вообще она может быть
I don't know Well like it was given to them by the Mongol
я не знаю Ну типа подарено монгольскими
mi for example
ми например
what
что
no Well I don't know but you know for sure
нет Ну я не знаю но ты знаешь наверняка
Yes I had no doubts Well because he was
Да я не сомневался Ну потому что он был
from the same Yes
из тех же самых Да
Turks he was
тюрков он был
Muslim I don't know if he was Muslim but
мусульман не знаю ли он был мусульман но
he was from these Turks yes it turns out
он был из тюрков этих
fun it turns out fun
да весело получается весело получается
so that's the question yes The question is that's why the
так вот вопрос да Вопрос поэтому
Arabic elm by the way look it means
и арабская вяз кстати смотри значит
at first they had it  naya writing and
сначала у них была нская письменность да
such special runes, then when they
рунами такими специальными вот потом при
adopted the Jurassic language, they had a Turkic
принятии и Юрский язык там был тюркский
language. And now it is not a ligature, look
язык у них И сейчас оно не вязь смотри
again, the Turkic languages ​​were first
ещё раз тюркские языки были сначала у
they had the so-called Arkhon script
них была Архонская письменность так
in Altai, it is the Turkic
называемая на Алтае она э тюркские
peoples from Altai came after the adoption of
народы с Алтая пошли после принятия
Islam, and the Arabic script spread among them. Well,
Ислама да у них распространилась
this is also in
арабская письменность Да ну это вот и в
Turkey before Mustafa Kemal Ataturk until the 20th
Турции до Мустафа кемаля ататюрка до XX
century. Yes, there was an Arabic script, then Mustafa
века Да была арабская вязь то Мустафа
Kemal Ataturk translated them into Latin. Yes,
кемаль Ататюрк перевёл их на латиницу Да
many Turks in Asia are Kazakhs there. And so
многие тюрки Азии там казахи И так
on, there, the Uzbeks also used
дальше там ээ узбеки также использовали
either the
либо
Chagatai Koran or not, that is the
чагатайский Коран там или нет такой
question. There is a Koran of the 6th century. No, but in the
вопрос Коран VI века есть Нет ну а в
Mongolian part, which means
монгольской части которому ему значит
look, look in Mongolia. Yes, in
смотри значит смотри в Монголии Да в
Mongolia there is no Islam in Mongolia, not Islam in
Монголии не ислам в Монголии не ислам во
Islam, I will say golden in the Golden Horde,
Ислам я скажу золотая в Золотой Орде
where did the Arabic spring come from, shlem, how did it
откуда арабская вясна шлеме как она
come, I explain, look, Islam in the
пришла объясняю значит смотри ислам в
golden family, if  I'm not mistaken, he came
золотой роде если я не ошибаюсь пришёл
under the
при
eh or under the tax mouse in the 10th century, I think,
ээ или при такса мыше в X веке по-моему
and then it split into Western and
он и тогда она распалась на Западную и
Eastern, so that's the point. Why does
Восточную так вот в чём суть Почему у
Russia not have a day of liberation from the Golden
России нету дня освобождение от Золотой
Horde? Because Russia is an
Орды потому что Россия - это и есть
organic part of the Golden Horde, it's just not.
органичная часть Золотой Орды просто не
And why is Ivan still Mongolian,
А почему Ивана всё-таки монгольская
not Mongolian, Arabic. Yes, Arabic,
весь не монгольская арабская Да арабская
because yes. Because he was essentially a Turk.
потому что да Потому что он был тюрк по
Yes, yes. I see. Okay, I agree. Well,
сути да Ага да Понятно Окей согласен ну
I think this is actually
это я считаю на самом деле это
wrong that we don't have a day of
неправильно что у нас нет дня
liberation from the Mongols. It seems to me that we
освобождения от Монгол Мне кажется нам
need a day of liberation from the Mongols and from the
нужен День освобождения и от Монгол и от
Poles and from the French, from everyone. Well,
Поляков и от французов вот от всех Ну
somehow, you see, there is no moment
вот как-то вот нету видишь нету момен
when the
когда
state that was the Russian
то государство которое было российской
Empire, the Muscovite kingdom, for
импери московским царством нету
some reason there is no moment when it again hung up,
почему-то момента когда снова зависа
developed, developed, there is no moment when it became
разви разви нету момента когда оно стало
independent. Why? Because it was.
независимым Почему Потому что оно и было
Yes, it was part of the Golden
Да оно и было часть Золотой
[music]
[музыка]
Horde. Maybe you know. And when did Russia
Орды може может знае А когда Россия вки
cease to be?
переста быть
Russia ceased to be.  dependent on the
есть Россия перестала быть зависимой от
Golden Horde No again Look you did
Золотой Орды Нет ещё раз Смотри ты же
n't
меня не не
hear me Russia didn't stop being
услышал Россия не перестала быть
dependent on the Golden Russia is
зависимой от Золотой Россия - это и есть
part of the golden Look there was the Soviet
часть золотой Вот смотри был Советский
Union
Союз
Yes so the State was
Да так вот Государство это вот была
golden there was the Golden Horde or here [ __ ] there
золотая была Золотая Орда или вот сри
was the Roman Empire it fell apart into
была Римская империя она развалилась на
there the Eastern Roman Empire something
там Восточную римскую Империю что-то
jumps out to the Soviet Union not to the
выпрыгивает к Советскому Союзу не на
Eastern and here it's better with these from the Roman
Восточную и тут лучше с эти с Римской
Empire because it's more logical it
империи потому что это логичнее она
fell apart into Western and Eastern Yes the
распалась на Западную и Восточную Да
Golden Horde also fell apart into
Золотая Орда также распалась на
Eastern Western Yes here
Восточную западную Да
is the Golden Horde Russia the Moscow
вот Золотая Орда Россия Московское
state never left the
государство никогда не выходила из
Golden Horde it became its logical
Золотой Орды она стала логичным её
continuation And why don't we have any
продолжением А почему у нас нет никаких
attributes at all culturally golden families
атрибутов вообще культурно золотой роды
as is what your money is called
как есть как называются ваши деньги
really money
правда деньги
why is it called money rubles No well
почему оно называется деньги рубли Не ну
money why is it called money
деньги почему оно называется деньги
correctly but rubles - What is this money
правильно но рубли - Это что это деньги
What is Where did the word money come from no
Что такое Откуда взялось слово деньги
Let's discuss What is a ruble Where
нет Давай обсудим Что такое рубль Откуда
in a ruble - this is your currency Yes a ruble is
в рубль - это валюта ваша Да рубль - это
from fellings  from the hryvnia here was the hryvnia
от рубок от гривны вот была гривна
where did we get the word currency look
откуда у нас взялось слово валюта смотри
also currency - it's from English yes And
ещё валюта - это из английской да А
where did the
откуда всего
word ruble come from Yes it's a cut from the hryvnia
слово рубль Да это отруба от гривны
because in Rus' in Kyiv there was a hryvnia Yes A cut from
потому что на Руси в Киеве была гривна
it It was a ruble Yes
Да От неё отруб Это был рубль Да
chopped hryvnia And where did the money come from Here you have
рубленая гривна А деньги откуда Вот вот
Yes for example look in SV look
у вас Да например смотри в СВ смотри
money you'll run away now Look this is not a
деньги ты сейчас убежишь Смотри это не
Slavic word money - it's a purely
Славянское слово деньги - это чисто
Turkic word here for example in wait no
тюркское слово вот например в подожди
wait again so I'm telling you now
нет подожди ещё раз так я тебе сейчас
when I speak you're silent it means
говорю когда я говорю ты молчишь значит
look the Kazakhs still have a currency
смотри у казахов до сих пор валюта
called tenge tenge Yes because
называется теньге теньге Да потому что
money money it was yes money Tribute It was in Turkic
деньги деньг это и было да деньг Дань
Why in your
Это и было по тюркски Почему в вашем
country the word money is Turkic
государстве слово деньги - это тюркское
because you because it was dependent
потому что вы потому что было зависимо
Well we were
Ну мы были
dependent for
зависи бы
years And why do we have words like
года А почему у нас есть слова типа
lampshade because we were dependent
абажур потому что мы были зависимы
on them Why not a lace you weren't
от от них Почему не а ажур вы не были
dependent on the French just a lampshade as an
зависимы от французов просто абажур как
interior element  came from France and that's
элемент интерьера пришёл из Франции да и
why you called it that Yes but money
поэтому вы так назвали Да но деньги не
couldn't come to you from the golden You did
могли к вам прийти из золотой У вас что
n't have your own
не было своих
money I'm saying we had our own ruble as
денег Я говорю у нас был свой рубль как
I said and the word money came to us
я и сказал а слово деньги пришло нам
perhaps from there I'm not arguing
возможно оттуда я Я не спорю
here M okay look uh The problem is
вот М хорошо смотри ээ Проблема в том
that this is you and there were this state
что это и есть вы и были это государство
with the word money yes to one word
со словом деньги да одному слову
you I'm telling you again Look this is a bunch of
ты Я тебе ещё раз говорю Смотри это куча
words by A thousand words how many with millions of
слов по Тысяча слов сколько с миллионы
words Yes look again once again no
слов Да смотри ещё раз ещё раз нет
look The point is that you Yes the most
смотри Суть в том что вы Да самый
key moment you don't have moments of
ключевой момент у вас нету моментов
leaving the Golden Horde you are the Golden
выхода из Золотой Орды вы и есть Золотая
Horde that's part of it that's all look
Орда вот э часть её вот и всё вот смотри
here and I a a
вот а я
look Let's do it this way I if
а вот смотри Давай вот так вот я если
Now I'll take I'll come to Kazakhstan And
Сейчас возьму приеду в Казахстан И
someone will start talking to me in
кто-то со мной начнёт общаться на
Kazakh I won't understand him you won't understand I
казахском я его не пойму не поймёшь я
can come I can come to Ukraine
могу приехать я могу приехать в Украину
I can come to Serbia I can
я могу приехать в сербию я могу приехать
even come to Poland and I'll understand them I'll
даже в Польшу и я их пойму правильно
explain why correctly Because you donkeys
объясняю почему Потому что вас ослов
Slavic language writing Yes, you
славянским языком письменность Да Вам
Kiev if you don't know about the Slavs sounds
при Киевский если ня о славяни звучит
like sorrow, yes, look, look Who is
как скорб да посмотри посмотри Кто такой
Feofan Prokopovich Yes, from Kyiv Yes, monks
Феофан Прокопович Да из Киева Да монахи
came there, brought you a letter,
приезжали туда несли вам письмо
brought the Cyrillic alphabet to us in Kyiv The Bulgarians
кириллицу нам в Киев принесли Болгары
Cyril and Methodius, they were Bulgarians, yes,
Кирилл и Мефодий они были болгарами да
they brought it, they
вот они принесли ходи не
were not Bulgarians And who
были болгарами А кем они
were they, they were
были они были
Macedonians, Macedonians, they brought it all over the world,
македон македонцы принесли по всему миру
they once Well, why not And once again, yes, yes, I
они раз Ну заче нет А ещё раз да да да я
stop, and they were Bulgarians, but the first, the
стоп а они были болгарами но первые
first, actually, all the prophets And all who
первые собственно все пророки И все кто
carried it in
несли
writing, they were all
собственно письменно они все были
Macedonians, they brought it all to you, Macedonians
македон к вам принесли вс
No, they were not Macedonians, they were
македон Нет они были не македон они
Ohrid The city of Ohrid Lake
были охрид Город охрид озеро
Ohrid is now the territory of Macedonia, it
охрид сейчас это территория македони
was Great Macedonia, it was not a
была Великая Македония это не было
concept, Great Macedonia There
понятия Великая Македония Вообще никогда
was never such a word, Great Macedonia,
не было такого слова Великая Македония
that means there was Clement of Ohrid Northern
вот значит был Климент охрид Северная
Macedonia Was There was Clement of Ohrid, yes,
Македония Была Был Климент охридский да
he had  followers of Kiri they were
у него были последователи Кири они были
Bulgarians look now now this is the
болгарами посмотри вот сейчас сейчас это
territory this is the territory of Macedonia Yes
территория это территория Македонии Да
but they were Bulgarians they came to this
но они были болгарами они пришли на это
they actually came there and from there
они собственно пришли туда и оттуда
actually Macedonians
собственно македонцы
they spread it to everyone so let me tell
они разнесли это всем поэтому давай я
you now look if now it
тебе сейчас открою смотри если сейчас
will be written Bulgarians Come on Kirill
будет написано Болгары Давай Кирилл
Kirill and Methodius You are
Кирилл и Мефодий Ты ж вообще
just O come on in Russian
просто О давай по-русски
as they say you snitch so so so
так как говорится вы снич так так
not this Bulgarians Yes Okay Bulgarians Bulgarians
так не это Болгары Да О'кей Болгары
Well they they personally brought m they personally
Ну они они лично принесли м они лично
here No well it's clear I don't Kirill they lived they
вот Не ну ясно Я нет Кирил они жили они
lived Neli their last and the
жили Нели их последни а
last were Macedonians these are Bulgarians everyone
последни были македон это Болгары всё
was then this is there The territory was
были тогда это там Территория была
captured by Bulgaria This is me in short look In short
захваченная Болгарией Это я короче смот
okay look I scout you again
Короче ладно смотри я тебе ещё раз скау
you asked why like they
ты спросил почему типа тебя в Казахстане
won't understand you in Kazakhstan but they will understand here because you O
не поймут а тут поймут потому что вас О
Slavs yes also for example you now for
славяни да также например ты сейчас
example Buryats Buryats yes which
например бурята бурята да который
uh and Ukraine and Slavs or or no no
ээ а Украину а славяни или или нет нет
we were Slavs With  what and with language
мы были славянами С какого и с язык у
we had and since time immemorial there have always been
нас был и спокон веков всегда были
Slavs Yes and the Moscow kingdom
славяне Да а а Московское царство
which was not Slavs
которое было не славяне
and Belgorod also no not Belgorod
и Белгородская тоже нет не Белгородская
region - these are Slavs there Ukrainians
область - это славяне там украинцы
Belgorod region Slavs look if
Белгородская область славя смотри если
you take a map of the settlement of the Slavs there in the
ты возьмёшь карту расселения славян там
91st century on the territory of the Moscow region
91 век на территории Московской области
the Slavs did not live like the Slavs they
славяне не проживали как вот славяне они
remained in such groups But here
вот такими кучками остались А вот а вот
we have here all the same not the same I will explain
тут у нас вот тут всё-таки не те объясню
let's look Buryats who now
давай так смотри буряты которые сейчас
essentially speak Russian yes
уже говорят по сути по-русски да
Buryat they almost do not know are they
бурятские они уже почти не знают они
Slavs or are they
славяне или они
Mongols
монголы
Well you you you can distinguish me from a
Ну ты ты ты можешь отличить меня от
Buryat again I asked let's tell me a
бурята ещё раз я спросил давай скажи мне
Buryat who speaks only
бурят который говорит уже только
Russian he is a
по-русски он
Slav No he is not Here he is about a Slav here he is about a Slav
славянин Нет он нет Вот он о славянин
Buryat now the question yes let's
вот он о славянин бурят теперь вопрос да
take the
возьмём
Udmurts I gave birth Let's do this I was born in
удмурты я родил Давай так я родился в
Moscow I am about Ukraine now look
Москве я я об Украине сейчас смотри ещё
again Udmurt  let's take now he already you ca
раз удмурт возьмём теперь он уже ты себя
n't tell yourself apart as a Russian from an Udmurt from a Ukrainian he is a European yes
сильно не отличишь он европеоид да
Udmurts who already speak essentially
удмурты которые уже говорят по сути
Russian they are
по-русски они
Slavs No they are not Slavs nope group
славяне Нет они не славяне нихя группа
pogo absolutely they look like that
пого абсолютно выглядят они так ты
take now an Udmurt yourself there on
возьми сейчас удмурта себя там на ещё
someone else me they look different how do they
кого-то меня по-другому выглядят как они
look well how like an Udmurt these are the
выглядят ну как как удмурта это там
same Turks there Udmurts are not Turks This is a Finno-
такие же тюрки удмурты не тюрки Это фино
Ugric people What Turks
угорский народ Какие тюрки
Well look Udmurt for example there is an
Ну смотри удмурт например вот там
Estonian Fin Udmurt ve like here they are Finno
эстонец Фин удмурт ве типа вот они фино
Ugrians Well they don't look the same as a
Угры Ну они выглядят не так же как
typical Russian person so typical Yes
типичный русский человек так типичный Да
now look further take Mordovia
вот теперь смотри дальше возьми Мордовия
people from Mordovia or from Maria L Yes from
людей из Мордовии или из Марии Л Да из
all these Finno-Ugric republics
всех вот этих фино угорских республик
They now already speak Russian what I mean Yes
Они сейчас уже говорят по-русски в чём Я
Listen just don't interrupt I want to get the
Да Слушай просто не перебивай я хочу
idea across yes with people in these
мысль донести да с люди в этих
republics Yes there Buryatia Udmurti and so on
республиках Да там Бурятия удмурти и так
they are
дальше они
already they are starting to speak a Slavic
уже они начинают говорить на славянском
language because  the ruling elite the
языке потому что правящая верхушка
ruling elite Yes,
правящая верхушка Да на славянском языке
they teach the office in the Slavic language And so on
делают обучение канцелярию И так дальше
Yes, on the territory of Moscow That is, in about
Да на территории Московской То есть
50-100 years you will already be an Udmurt and
через там лет 50-100 уже ты удмурта и
this and Maritsa and how is it Mordvin Yes, you will not
этого и Марица и как оно мордов да не
distinguish it from Russian
отличишь от Русского
They will all speak Russian and
Они все будут говорить по-русски и
look approximately the same So, the
выглядеть приблизительно одинаково так
inhabitants of the modern Moscow region Yes,
вот жители Московской области
Yaroslavl That's all in
современной Да Ярославской Вот это Все
short Vologda Ivanovo where that was
короче Вологодской Ивановское где вот
there Moscow principality
это было там Московское княжество
Vladimir principality they were not
Владимирское княжество они не были
Slavs Slavic there was only uh
славянами славянским там был только ээ
during Kievan Rus Yes, when the prince
во время Киевской Руси да Когда князь
who was sent from Kyiv his task was to
которого присылали из Киева его задача
collect tribute was the same as, for example,
собирать Дань было так же как например
Murom the city of Murom was called so no, he was a
Муром город Муром назван так нет он был
Fino Ugm who Well, this is a Rurikovich Yes,
же фино угм кто Ну это же рюрикович Да
but he was a
но он был рюриковичей
follower of the Rurikovichs Once again, what Fino Ugrians
последователем Ещё раз какие фино Угры
Well, Prince Irriko HIV Prince Yurikovich was a
Ну князь иррико ВИЧ князь юрикович был
Fino Ugm you said it yourself I have
фино угм ты же сам сказал я такого в
never
жизни не
said such a thing in my life Okay, so look, the prince who
говорил О'кей значит смотри князь
came from  Kyiv is essentially
который приезжал из Киева это по сути
like a governor Yes, for
как губернатор Да вот губернатора
example, the governor was sent to the Irkutsk region Yes,
прислали например в иркутскую область Да
he governs or the governor was sent to
он управляет или губернатора прислали в
Buryatia He did not become a Buryat because of this Yes,
бурятию Он от этого бурятам не стал да
well, and the princes Yes, they sent their
Ну да и князья Да отправляли туда своих
sons there not with a small army Yes, but they lived
сыновей не с небольшим войском Да а жили
there, they lived absolutely different other
там жили да абсолютно разные другие
peoples and it’s very simple Yes, you
народы и вот очень просто да вот у вас
have a city in Russia Galich, it’s now
есть в России город Галич он сейчас
called Galich Yes, before the revolution it was also
называется Галич да до революции он ещё
called Galich the vile Yes,
назывался там Галич мерзкий Да потому
because also Murom Yes, because the
что также Мурома да потому потому что
Merya tribe lived there, the city of Murom is named
жило там племя меря город Муром назван
after the Finno-Gorsko tribe Murom
по племени фино горско Муром
so the city of Ryazan is the territory of the
так город Рязань - это территория
Erzya tribe Erzya Moksha is Mordvin
племени эрзя эрзя мокша - это Мордва
if we look Yes, also Arzamas is
если мы посмотрим Да также Арзамас это
Erzya mas the city of
эрзя мас город
Erz No, Aza sounds like yes, yes So
эрз Не ну Аза звучит как будто да да Так
Ku This is the Caucasus no, no, it’s not
Ку Это Кавказ нет не это нет это не
Caucasian it’s the RNS name
кавказское это рнс название
Erma porno as if you know there like
эрма проно как будто знаешь там типа
some kind of well, when with the letters a it became Yes, that’s the
какой-то ну когда с буквами а стало Да
thing that on the territory of the
вот и дело в том что на территории
Moscow region and so on, non-
Московской области и так дальше жили не
Slavs lived Yes there  was from the Slavs only
славяне Да там был из славян только
sent from Kyiv this posadnik yes
присылал из Киева вот этот посадник да
kie No well and why all the same Well
кие Не ну а почему всё-таки Ну похожи
nations are similar to each other Well once because it's
друг на друга нации Ну раз потому что
all European
это это всё европеоидная
European type look if we
европеоидный тип смотри если мы
look
посмотрим
also no again no Look the Mongols
тоже нет ещё раз нет Смотри монголы -
are
это
Mongol you said that they now they
Монгол ты сказал что они сейчас они
in 100 years will become the same Russian
через 100 лет станут такими же русскими
in language and here all these look Udmurts And
по языку а вот эти все смотри удмурты И
so on Yes you won't tell them apart they are
так дальше Да ты их не отличишь они
Europeans they will speak a Slavic
европеоиды будут говорить на славянском
language moreover if if you
языке во больше того если если ты
look like this Bulgarians Bulgarians they Who are
посмотришь так Болгары Болгары они Кто
these Turks
это тюрки
ki who came from the Volga region through the
ки которые пришли с Поволжья через
steppe territory of modern Ukraine
территорию степную современной Украины
here the Bulgarian Khan Asparukh
вот болгарский Хан аспарух ещё под
died near Zaporozhye and came what a question I
Запорожьем погиб и пришли накой вопрос я
just well a little ahead we I'll run
просто ну чуть-чуть наперёд мы я забегу
and the French and not the Turks No they are a mixture of
а французы а не тюрки Нет они смесь
Gauls and Germanic tribes
галов и германских племён
PM Gaul - it was a Roman province
ПМ Галия - это была Римская провинция
conquered by Caesar Yes here  then the
завоёвана Цезарем Да вот потом Империя
Frankish Empire okay okay I agree everything is here here
франков лад Хорошо согласен всё тут тут
I am here here I will not discuss Yes In short
я тут тут Я обсуждать не буду Да Короче
okay The point is what Let's do it this way I'll tell my friend about
ладно Суть в чём Давай так я подру про
Russia I wait I'll cut about Russia
Росси я по подожди я подрез про Россию
Now yes in Russia yes those who are
Сейчас да в России да тех кого называют
now called Russians Yes these are just different
сейчас русскими Да это просто разные
peoples there are Turkic Finno-Ugric others
народы там тюркские фино угорские другие
who are about Slavs to whom the written
которые о славяни которым письменный
language was brought from Kyiv yes Kyiv
язык принесли из Киева да киевские
monks this is a fact no Udmurts call themselves
монахи это это факт нет удмурты называют
Udmurta Let's do it no Udmurts
себя удмурта Давай се нет удмурты себя
call themselves tyaka
называют тяка
Well I know I know two or three people yes
Ну я зна Я знаю человека два или три да
three who call themselves Udmurt Because because
три которые называют себя удмурт Потому
in the 20th century Yes they were
что потому что в XX веке Да им их Лени
called Leni Udmurts And that's what they were called And that's
назвали удмурты И вот так их называли А
how they were called vatki not me of
так они назывались ватки не у меня ещё
course it's interesting you do
конечно интересно
n't define yourself as Russian of course
себя не определяешь конечно же русским
you define yourself as Ukrainian I am Ukrainian
ты себя определяешь украинцем Я украинец
yes Yeah okay and accordingly you
да Ага вот окей а соответственно ты
said that Russians are Udmurts and well
сказал что русские - это и удмурты и ну
all that all that are modern yes those who are
всес всес которы современны да те тех
called Russians in modern
кого называют русскими в современном
understanding yes that is those that is Russian
понимании да то есть тех то есть русский
- these are those who are called Russians look
- это тех кого называют русскими смотри
So understand you are Russian I will explain No I
Значит поняти ты русский объясню Нет я
called you Russian So you are Russian you are
назвал тебя русским Значит ты русский ты
now
сейчас
simply because look I smashed you
просто потому что смотри я тебя разнёс
Pus and crash and you are trying to glue chka
Пус и крах и ты пробуешь клеить чка
then look the modern concept
значит смотри современное понятие
Russians those that this is in the census Yes these are
русские те что вот это в перепись Да это
absolutely different peoples that were at a
абсолютно разные народы которые были в
certain moment about Slavs Yes they
определённый момент о славянин Да им
were brought uh Christianity
принесено было ээ христианство
Orthodoxy from Kyiv And to Kyiv from
православие из Киева А в Киев из
Constantinople Yes the
Константинополя Да принесена была э
Cyrillic alphabet was brought and the
кириллическая Азбука и сделан был
Church Slavonic language was created in which, in
церковнославянский язык на котором по
fact, the divine service was conducted there
сути велось богослужение
were letters yes and thus the
письмена были да и таким образом
modern Russian language was formed
сформировался современный русский язык
Yes look It is very simple in the
Да вот и посмотри Очень просто в
Ukrainian language we write milk and
украинском языке мы пишем молоко и
read milk as we write So We read
читаем молоко как пишем Так Читаем
Russians write as we brought them a
русские пишут так как мы им принесли
letter Well not us but the ancestors like those people
письмо Ну не мы а предки типа тех людей
who lived here Well yes Zarya you
которые вот тут жили Ну да заря ты
say that Slavs should be talked about
говорит что славянина надо говорить об
Ukraine No no not about Ukraine Because it was
украини Нет не не об Украине Потому что
not the Ukrainians who brought it there but let's
не украинцы да принес туда а
say  the people who lived on the
скажем тот народ который жил на
territory of Rus' then there were no
территории Руси тогда не было ещё
Ukrainians yet yes that is Ukrainians as a nation
украинцев да то есть украинцы как нация
from it How to correctly call Ukrainians Ukrainians
из него Как правильно украинцев называть
Well about Ukraine no you are not about Ukraine
украинцы Ну об украини нет вы не об
damn you are about the Slavs about the
Украине блин вы о славяни о славянина да
Slav yes about the Slav yes That is to say to you we will say so va
о славянина да То есть Вам скажем так ва
you are not a branch of Ukrainians
скажем вы не есть веткой украинцев
Uno so look Why in the Russian
Уно так вот и посмотри Почему в русском
language you Chita write milk and read
языке Вы Чита пишете молоко а читаете
milk because the letter was brought to you
молоко потому что письмо вам принесено
from here it was like here in Kievan
отсюда было так как вот тут в Киевской
Rus they wrote
Руси писали
milk with the letters o and read milk
молоко через буквы о и читали молоко
because as it used to be how it was written
потому что как раньше было как писалось
and read well they wrote letters according to
так и читалось ну писали буквы по
phonetics in the Russian language because
фонетике вот в русском языке из-за того
these Finno-Ugric tribes lived there
что там жили вот эти фино угорские
Yes they couldn't speak like that
племена Да они не могли вот так говорить
they had and that's why milk That's why
у них было и поэтому молоко Поэтому вот
all these unstressed o A long time ago A long time ago you
эти все безударные о А давно А давно ты
were somewhere
был где-нибудь
in a
в
village in Siberia where no one ever directly tells you
деревне в Сибири где прямо тебе никто
if someone ever tells you
никогда если тебе кто-то когда-то скажет
say milk in Omsk well you will be beaten up
условно в Омске молоко ну тебя побьют
right away because you Moscow about po Any
сразу потому что ты Моск об по Любой
person will say molo because
человек вонс скажет моло потому что
Siberia
Сибирь
yes, this is not the autochthonous population of Siberia,
да это не автохтонное население сиби
look, Siberia has settled Yes, for several centuries,
смотри Сибирь засе Да несколько веков в
including many people from
том числе многими выходцами из Украины
modern Ukraine Yes, Siberia,
современной Да Сибирь Сибирь заселяли да
Siberia was settled, yes, look, Siberia was settled Yes,
посмотри Сибирь заселяли
most of the people from Ukraine were not from some Vologda
большинство не из Вологодской какой-то
region and that's why Oka is also
области и всё поэто тоже Оку поэтому и
in the Urals Oka is also in the Urals Hurray, who are there in the
на Урале Оку поэтому на Урале Ура во хто
Russians Where are there in the Urals in the
на в русских нету Где там на Урале на
Urals different other peoples, look, there are the
Урале разные другие народы смотри там
Japanese, no, in the Urals, Tatars in the
там там японцы нет на Урале татары на
Urals, Chuvash Yes, where in the Urals were the original
Урале Чуваши Да где на Урале исконно
Russians Well, that's a
русские
good
были Ну хороший
question The Urals are not Slavic
вопрос Урал - это не Славянская
territory Well, come on, come on, I'll say that
территория Ну давай да давай я скажу что
in Penza, Penza is also Penza -
в Пензе Пенза - это тоже Пенза - это
damn, it's not Slavic The very name Penza
блин не Славянская само название Пенза
Well, although, although, although, if Bulgaria is
Ну хотя хотя да хотя если Болгария это
ki, then maybe, well, Penza is also not Penza Perm Perm
ки то может ну Пенза тоже не Пенза Пермь
is also a tribe Perm was, yes,
Пермь - это тоже племя Пермь было да
Permyaks, and Bulgaria is the Turks But  don't
Пермяки а Болгария - это тюрки Но не
laugh and where did the Bulgarians come from By the way, you
смейся и откуда Болгары пошли Кстати ты
know what Volga Bulgaria is
знаешь что такое Волжская Булгария
By the way, you also know
кстати тоже знаешь
mm Volga Bulgaria
мм Волжская Булгария
Yes, a state on the territory of Yes,
Да государство на территории Да
modern Tatarstan Chuvashia Yes, with a
современного Татарстана Чувашии Да со
capital in the city Well, there was a resettlement
столицей в городе Ну там переселение
I don't know something like that the most
было я не знаю что-то типа того
powerful state of its time Yes,
мощнейшее государство своего времени да
when the Tatar-Mongols like well, it
когда татаро-монголы типа ну оно
essentially ceased to exist under the
прекратила по сути существования под
onslaught of the Tatar-Mongols no let's go back
натиском татаро-монгол не давай вернёмся
to the language Well, you let us down Why is Russia this
к языку Ну ты подводил Почему Россия это
look again we we already Yes, with you and
смотри ещё раз мы мы уже Да с тобой и
were Why are you a continuation of the Horde Why are
были Почему вы продолжение Орды Почему
you not Slavs And so on And so on So that's
вы не славяне И так дальше И так дальше
what I wanted come on come on So
так вот к чему я хотел давай давай Так
undercut you yes you
подрез вы да вы
Asia no need to be ashamed of this Mongolia
Азия не надо этого стесняться Монголия
No, not Mongolia I didn't say Mongolia ri
Нет не Монголия я не говорил Монголия ри
part of the Great Horde once again once again
часть Великой злотой Орды ещ раз ещё раз
Asia Yes, this is a very broad
ещё раз Азия Да это очень широкое
concept This is not Mongolia this is not Kazakhstan this is not Skha this is
понятие Это не Монголия это не Казахстан
not Bashkartastan in Asia
это не Сха это не башкартастан в Азии Да
Yes, there are a huge number of different peoples
огромное количество разных народов есть
Mongolian peoples Yes, there are those Buryats,
монгольские народы Да вот эти там буряты
Mongols, Kalmyks Yes, there is a Turkic people,
монголы калмыки Да есть тюркский народ
Kazakhs, Tatars, these are sweats And so on Well,
казахи татары это поты И так дальше Ну
you probably also understand In what
ты же тоже наверное понимаешь В каком
context In Russia, people are in
контексте В России люди находятся в
what that people in Russia watch the same
каком что люди в России смотрят те же
Western films, listen to the same Western
западные фильмы слушают тех же западных
actors, wear what in Kazakhstan In
актёров носят что в Казахстане в
Kazakhstan, they watch Western films, wear They
Казахстане смотрят западные фильмы носят
sit on the Western Internet that in Kazakhstan,
Западном интернете сидят что в
everything is much more shifted towards
Казахстане сильно более всё смещено туда
China, they watch Thai films in
Китаю тайские фильмы смотрят в
Kazakhstan much more than they do
Казахстане сильно больше чем это делают
in Moscow, no stop, stop, stop, wait, stop
в Москве нет стоп стоп стоп подожди стоп
In Kazakhstan as part of the post-Soviet
в Казахстан как часть постсоветского
space Yes, they also watch
пространства Да также смотрит там и
Russian-language films and American
русскоязычные фильмы и американские
films there, and so on What China What are you, well,
фильмы и так дальше какой Китай Ты что
okay, I'm okay, I'll say Yes, in
ну О'кей я я Окей я скажу Да в
Kazakhstan They also watch this
Казахстане Тоже смотрят это
territorially, this does not make
территориально это не делает
Kazakhstan Europe Well, but territorially,
Казахстан Европой Вот но территориально
for now, Russia is partly in Europe
пока Россия часть находится в Европе
Territorially, you agree with this,
Территориально ты согласен с этим
partially, part of Russia, part of Russia
частично часть России часть России
is in Europe just like part of
находится в Европе так же как и часть
Turkey is in Europe True, yes, yes, that's it Well, for
Турции находится в Европе правда да да
now, This is the main part in which,
вот Ну пока Это основная часть в которой
well, not 90%, let's say so, live  70 Well,
проживает ну не 90% ну скажем так 70 Ну
from 50 to 70%, and in Russia, in
от 50 до 70% так и в России в это в
Turkey, yes, in Turkey, in Istanbul, in Istanbul, the
Турции да в Турции в Стамбуле в Стамбуле
majority, yes, lives in Istanbul, in
большинство да живёт в Стамбуле в
Istanbul, definitely does not live in Istanbul,
Стамбуле точно не проживает в Стамбуле
about a huge agglomeration, Well, how many are there,
про огромная агломерация Ну сколько там
well, mi million 5 10 15 Of how many,
ну ми миллионов 5 10 15 Из скольки там
even the third, and look, and then there is the
даже третья а та смотри та дальше там
mountainous part of the mountainous and deserted part
Горная часть горной и пустынной часть ти
of Turkey, yes, that is, the main part, too,
по Турции да то есть основная часть тоже
we will see because there was a
мы посмотрим потому что там была
civilization, that is, this does not make it
цивилизация то есть от этого не делается
True, Well, okay, we, and no, and the Turks, they, uh, Well,
Правда Ну окей мы А нет а турки они э
okay, maybe, maybe, I can kind of
Ну окей возможно возможно я могу как бы
admit to myself that I confuse
вот про себя признать что я путаю
Eurocentrism
европоцентризм
that Russia is Europe, that's me, I
что Россия - Это Европа вот я Я как
understand from your side it
понимаю с твоего с твоей стороны это
looks like that, but from my side, what
выглядит но с моей стороны всё-таки то
you're doing is just some kind of
чем ты занимаешься Это просто какой-то
very fierce chere, when you choose
очень лютый чере когда ты вот выбираешь
only what's convenient for you, Let's
только то что тебе удобно Давай
see, then look, let's do it, the
посмотрим значит смотри давай так у вате
Minister of Defense was in Vate, step, Come on, No, you
министр обороны был шагу Давай Нет
can, let's see about
можешь ещё раз давай посмотрим про
mentalities again, Yes, Europe or Asia, step,
ментальности Да Европа или Азия шагу
we step
мы шагу
he come on look was he was We had it
он давай посмотри был он был Был у нас
now well Now let's do it this way Kadyrov
сейчас хорошо Теперь давай так Кадыров
Kadyrov is generally Chechnya is not
Кадыров - это вообще Чечня - это не
Russia they themselves want to
Россия они сами хотят
separate then this one is from Ingushetia
отделиться потом этот это из ингушети
this yuk or what is he for minister of defense
этот юк или как он за министр обороны
or who is he
или кто он
Yevkurov no stop but but if we have
Евкуров нет стоп а вот а если мы вот у
Belousov now come on straight from
нас сейчас Белоусов давай вот прямо с
Belo so look what I mean what I mean what in
бело так смотри я я к чему име я к чему
theory you should change your mind What I'm
по идее ты должен сменить мнение Я к
getting at is that you have a huge amount
чему веду что у вас огромное количество
Yes also uh these Asian
Да также э вот этих азиатского
components it is there yes you have more than that
компонента оно есть да у вас больше того
look under Peter I there
смотри при Петре I
is both Asia and Europe look Look in
есть и Азия и Европа смотри Смотри
short what I'm getting at before Peter I you were
короче к чему я веду до Петра I вы были
completely Asia completely Asia were yes
полностью Азией полностью Азии были да
you were just a part completely Asia
вы были просто частью полностью Ази
completely Asia were yes Peter I Yes when
полностью Азии были да Пётр I Да когда
after the war with the Swedes when he got
после войны со шведами когда он получил
access to the Baltic Sea Yes that's only then
выход к балтийскому морю Да вот только
still Say they cut a window to
тогда то ещё Говори прорубили Окно в
Europe this is being said about Peter I yes
Европу это ж говорится про Петра I да
then he because after all he
тогда он потому что вот всё-таки он
studied there in the goal  then he completely
учился там в гола тогда он полностью
took the course on Europeanization Yes, he forced the boyars to
взял курс на европеизации Да боярам
shave their beards You know this Yes, to
заставлял брить бороды Ты же знаешь это
look European they began to
да выглядеть по-европейски начали
invite European uh here these
приглашать европейских ээ сюда этих
enlighteners European scientists so that
просветителей европейских учёных чтобы
European engineers And so on and so forth Yes, that
европейских инженеров И так дальше да то
is, completely That's why by the way all the
есть полностью Поэтому вот кстати все
Lermontovs appeared the Lermontov family and so on and so
появились лермонтовых рода лермонт и так
forth Yes, a huge number
и куча других Да огромное количество
if we look at the Russian Empire at
если мы посмотрим Российская империя в
the time of its collapse in 1917 there were
момент своего крушения в 1917 году там
all some officer ranks all this all
все офицерские какие-то чины все это всё
this was In short, they were not Russians they were not
это были Короче не русские это были не
Russians Well, it was a provincial
русские Да ну это была Провинциальная
part of Europe to which
часть Европы в которую приезжали
some miracles came No, wait, look, for
какие-то чуды Нет ну подожди про смотри
example, the mathematician mathematician
например
Leonard
математи математик математик Леонард
Euler also lived for a certain time in
Эйлер тоже жил определённое время в
St. Petersburg he was invited, he was paid there
Петербурге его приглашали платили он там
Prival did something there and so on and so forth Yes, that
Привал что-то там делал и так дальше да
is, it was an attempt to become Europe
то есть это была попытка стать Европой
Yes, the Soviet Union Yes, the Soviet Union
Да Советский Союз Да Советский Союз
when the Soviet Union happened, it combined
когда случился Советский Союз э сочетал
in itself uh part and European Yes,
в себе ээ часть и европейской Да потому
because it was Uh, which was founded by
что он Ээ как бы который был основан
Lenin yes E no, not Lenin  you could
Лениным да Э нет не Лениным можно так
say Lenin was one of those
сказать бы Ленин был один из тех э
players in this Yes, well, Lenin was a Tatar
игроков в этой Да ну Ленин татарином был
No, Lenin is not a Tatar Lenin was
Да нет Ленин не татарин Ленин был
partly Chuvash, partly Jewish, so Lenin is
частично чуваш частично еврей вот Лени
not a Tatar and you ask many Chuvash,
не татары и ты у многих чувашей спроси
they know for sure and I study this with them
они точно знают и у них это изучаю
Armenians Armenians yes, they have everything, yes, they have everything, and
Армян Армян да у них все да у них все и
Lenin is an Armenian and so on That's how you
Ленин армян и так дальше Вот так вот
look at the Soviet Union Yes, in its essence, it
смотри Советский Союз Да по своей сути
was not just European or Asian
был не то что европейским иле азий Ским
The task of the Soviet Union from the point of view of
задача Советского Союза с точки зрения
its creators was to be
его создателей он должен быть
international, that is, it is a new
интернациональным то есть это новая
community Yes, it should have been Soviet
общность Да должна была Советский
man should have been, that is, here when the
человек должен бы то есть тут когда
Soviet Union collapsed Yes, we are in
Советский Союз распался Да мы по
Belarus, this is a complete
Беларусь вот это полностью
component Yes, the Baltics are European Ukraine A
компонент Да Балтика Европейский Украина
European component with some We
Европейский компонент с небольшими У нас
have Crimea Crimea is still
есть Крым Крым всё-таки
those Polovtsians and then who
это есть те половцы да потом которые
began to be called Crimean Tatars Yes,
стали называться крымскими татарами Да
this is Asia in essence, and more than that The
это Азия по сути да больше
steppe part of Ukraine Yes, the Kherson
того Степная часть Украины Да Херсонская
region is part of the Soda And so on
область там часть соде И так дальше
until,
до
say, the Grand Duchy of Lithuania in
скажем Великого княжества Литовского по
essence, yes, that was also  Turkic lands, here
сути да это было тоже тюркские земли вот
we have Odessa Yes, as they say, Odessa was
у нас Одесса Да как говорят там Одессу
created by Katerina there was a Turkic city of
создала Катерина там было тюркской город
Khadzhibey The fact is that this
Хаджибей Дело в том что вот эта
territory of modern Ukraine, which is at the
территория современной Украины которая
bottom of the steppe, was not inhabited by
внизу степи она не была населена
Slavs
славянами
There, Turkic tribes lived for thousands of years It
там Тысячи лет жили тюркские племена Это
was a migration route from west to
был миграционный путь из запада на
east, that is, Ukraine in its
восток то есть Украина в своём
historical context, here in our
историческом контексте вот в нашей
territory Yes, we have Yeah, part of the Donetsk
территории Да у нас Угу часть Донецкой
region, part of the Kharkov region, part of the
области часть Харьковской области часть
Zaporozhye region, part of the Kherson region,
Запорожской часть Херсонской
Nikolaev and Odessa, these were Turkic
Николаевской и Одесской это тюркские
territories if we look in and
было территории если мы посмотрим в а
now no, now no Yes, now they
теперь нет теперь нет Да теперь там
live there like Since what moment now no E
живут типа С какого момента теперь нет Э
since the moment when look in uh when the
с момента когда смотри в ээ когда
Lithuanian prince uh I don't remember Or Mindoh
литовский князь ээ не помню Или миндох
or Ol defeated the Tatars Mongol under the
или Оль победил э татар Монгол под
blue waters or what Yes, he recaptured
синими водами или что Да он отбил вот
this territory of Kievan Rus it became
эту территорию Киевской Руси она пошла в
part of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and
состав Великого княжества Литовского и э
in the Nikolaev region yes, in Nikolaev I
в Николаевской области да в Николаеве не
can't let's do it this way so as not to deceive either
могу давай так чтобы не обмануть или сам
Nikolaev himself or that is, that is, you  you say
Николаев или то есть то есть ты говоришь
that as soon as the Lithuanians
что как только литовцы
captured they reached the Black Sea they
захватили они на Чёрное море вышли они
reached the Black Sea as soon as the Lithuanians
вышли до Чёрного моря как только литовцы
captured Ukraine Ukraine
захватили Украину Украина
ceased to exist Lithuanians did not
перестала перестала существовать литовцы
No Lithuanians did not capture Ukraine
не Нет литовцы не захватывали Украину
independent Kievan Rus ceased to
независимая Киевская Русь перестала
exist when the Mongols attacked yes
существовать когда напали монголы да
Lithuanians Yes when they recaptured this territory from the Mongols
литовцы Да когда отбили у Монгол эту
Yes we ended up
территорию Да мы попали
in the state of the Grand Duchy of
в в государство Великое княжество
Lithuania in some sources
Литовское в некоторых джерелах источника
it was called the Grand Duchy of
она называлась великое князивство
Lithuania Russian and Samogitian the
литовский русский и жемайтис
official language in the Duchy of Lithuania
официальным языком в княжестве литовском
was the language of Kievan Rus Russian the language was
было язык Киевской Руси русско мова
written in this Yes there was also
писалась на этом Да там также было и
Orthodoxy and other then when the
православие и другое потом когда
Duchy of Lithuania united with Poland Yes it became the
княжество Литовское Да стала реч
Commonwealth the Commonwealth we became in
посполита речь посполитая мы стали в
one state with the Poles Lithuanians
одном государстве с поляками литовцами
yes that is yes So the Lithuanian prince Yes
да то есть да Так вот литовский князь Да
reached the Black Sea on the Black Sea
вышел до Чёрного моря на Чёрном море
was near Odessa it was I don't remember how
было возле Одессы было не помню как
Nikolaev was also there near Nikolaev Who from Nikolaev will
Николаев тоже там возле Николаева Кто из
say how  it's called a
Николаева скажет как называется
settlement here I heard myself Come on
поселение вот я сам себя услышал Давай
far Wait look in the Kharkov
даль Подожди смотри в Харьковской
region near the city of Izyum where there were
области возле города изюм в котором были
military actions Yes there are statues here you
боевые действия Да вот есть статуи вот
know Polovtsian women balbals they are
эти знаешь половецкие бабы балбалы их
called there by the Kazakhs they are called balbals
называют там казахи их называют балбалы
Turks Yes it was a Turkic territory
тюрки Да это была тюркская территория
bordering with this with Russia yes that is if
погранич с этим с Русью да то есть если
we look 300 years ago on the
мы посмотрим ещё 300 лет назад по
territory of there Odessa region there
территории там Одесской области там
Nikolaev region camels passed caravans
Николаевской за про ходили верблюды
with camels walked yes that is
караваны с верблюдами ходили да то есть
And this territory it is called Kicha
И вот эта территория он называется кича
Kipchak Kaya steppe de Kipchak If you
кипчак кая степь де кипчак Если ты
look at the physical map of the world Yes
посмотришь на физическую карту мира Да
there is exactly the steppe goes there from Mongolia
там именно степь идёт туда от Монголии
here goes under Ukraine and a little here behind the
сюда идёт под Украину и чуть сюда за за
Danube a little so wait these these
Ду навия немножко так вот подожди эти
territories were here the south of Ukraine They
эти территории были вот юг Украины Они
were for centuries migration routes
были столетиями миграционными путями э
from Asia there to the rich regions there of the
из Азии в туда в богатые регионы там
Roman Empire in Noni And so on the
Римской империи в Нони И так дальше
Hungarians Yes also for a certain
венгры Да тоже ээ определённое
number of years were on the territory of
количество лет были на территории
modern Ukraine in  southern regions Yes,
современной Украины в южных областях Да
they stood in a camp then passed
вот Они табором стояли потом прошли там
through the Carpathians Bulgarians also passed Yes and
через Карпаты Болгары также прошли Да и
a lot of other things, therefore and in the end In the end
куча всего поэтому и в итоге В итоге
look We are Ukrainians Yes we
смотри Мы украинцы Да мы объективно
look at our history objectively We have a part,
смотрим на свою историю У нас есть часть
this is Crimea which
это есть Крым который
uh
ээ по
essentially is Aziz in its own logic Yes, but we do not
сути Азис по своему логике Да по мы не
deny this, yes and you are Russians Yes you do not
отрицаем этого да а вы русские Да вы не
perceive it you somehow want to
воспринимаете вы как-то хотите
disown
открестился
This is Europe This is certainly not Europe but it is
Это Европа Это конечно не Европа но
stupid to talk
глупо говорить
Of course we can gain some
Конечно мы можем набрать каких-то
facts not the Mongols are great Okay I Speak
факто не монголи великим Окей я Говори
accordingly It seems to me that this is
соответственно Мне кажется что это
still too much
всё-таки перебор
I would actually I would really
вот я я бы на самом деле я бы очень
like to do something conditionally if you
хотел что сделать условно если вот ты
like such conversations there to
любишь такие вот разговоры там
talk on streams I would still
поговорить на стримах Я бы всё-таки
prepare And I would
подготовился И хотел с тобой вот
really like to talk to you too having
действительно поговорить тоже вот
prepared some information Because
подготовив какую-то информацию Потому
what are you actually
что ты что ты собственно там
talking about You are my channel You
разговаривал Ты же мой канал
know in fact no I
Знаешь на самом деле нет я как будто
was like once
один раз был
but
но
what Andrey is the beginning and
какой Андрей початка и
so there are two channels on YouTube Yes take there for
так есть два канала в юбе Да возьми там
example in this there is a link to Telegram
например в этом есть ссылка на Telegram
chat and  there is a link to the chatbot in the Telegram chat,
чат а в Telegram чате есть ссылка на
that is, I can write to
чатбот то есть мне можно туда написать в
this chatbot there, for example, you can
этот чатбот да например ты можешь
send, for example, about we can contact each other on Zoom,
скинуть например о можем там по Зуму
Skype, it doesn't matter where, we'll
Скайпе неважно где-то связаться по это
choose some time because
как оно выберем какой-то час потому что
I'm interested in conversations Not
мне интересны как раз разговоры Не
just some in front of me, I
просто какие-то пред меня просто меня
just need to go to bed and
просто уже как бы надо спать идти и
tomorrow morning it's early Continue pouring out
завтра с утра Рано Продолжи сыпаться
That's why I can't do anything special here without facts,
Поэтому я тут собственно без фактов не
look, the topic is very
могу ничего особо смотри те тема очень
interesting You took it
интересная Ты сначала Это воспринимал
as a joke at first Yes, you wanted to translate it there,
как-то в шутку Да ты там хотел это
like, yes The topic is very interesting,
Перевести типа да Тема очень интересная
very deep, yes The question The question is that, let's
очень глубокая да Вопрос Вопрос в том
say, so the undercut Turkic
что ээ скажем ээ так подрез тюркские
peoples and the Slavic Slavic peoples
народы и Слав славянские народы очень
interacted very strongly Yes, because
сильно взаимодействовали Да потому что
we, Rus', were on the border with the Turkic world
мы Русь была погранич с тюркским миром
Yes, in the Kyiv prince's service there were
Да в э у Киевского князя были на службе
Polovtsians, there were different Berendeys, you have Berendey Polyany, something like that, yes
половцы были там берендеи разные вот у
Okay, you also have Berendey Polyany,  it's
Окей тоже есть такой берендеевы Поляны у
called where in the Moscow region
вас называется где в Московской области
or in the Yaroslavl region somewhere there is that is
или в Ярославской где-то там есть то
Maybe there is I don't know Yes it's
есть Может есть я не знаю Да это по
named after the southern tribe of the Berendeys And so
южскому племени берендеев названо И так
on so then I hope that we will
дальше так что тогда я надеюсь что мы
still get in touch super if it will be
всё-таки свяжемся супер если если будет
interesting write to the chatbot in Telegram we
интересно пиши в чатбот в Telegram
will agree on everything
договоримся всё
let's if I remember Uda it was an
давай если как вспомню Уда
interesting conversation yes At first it was
интересный был разговор да Сначала он
somehow very all in jest At what
как-то очень всё в шутку При какой
Turgenev what kind of damn Russian p
Тургенев какой этот блин русский п
look Yeah it goes back to the
смотришь Ага восходит от
Tatar clan when the Tatar Murza
татарского рода когда татарский Мурза
Lev Turgen accepted baptism and became Ivan
Лев турген принял крещение и стал Иван
Turgen yes Lermon what Lermon Lermon
тургене да лермон какой лермон лермон
Scotsman And so on Yes therefore
шотландец И так дальше Да поэтому
modern Russia is such a
современная Россия - это такой
conglomerate here modern Russian is
конгломерат вот современный русский это
just such a cauldron of completely different
просто такой котёл из абсолютно разных
peoples Yes which are simply about a Slav to
народов Да которые просто о славянин
whom the Slavic language Yes it will bring it
которым язык Славянский Да принесёт это
all the same that look now the Buryats the
всё равно что вот смотрите сейчас буряты
Buryats speak Russian now they almost do
буряты говорят сейчас по-русски почти
n't know Buryat They don't
уже не знают бурятского Они же не
stop being Mongols Yes they are just
перестают быть монголами Да они просто
Mongols and a Slav Yes also  and all the
монголы а славянин Да также и всё
Volga region Yes, all these are all Turkic
Поволжье Да всё вот эти все это тюркские
Finno-Ugric peoples who are just
фино угорские народы которые просто
now starting to speak the Slavic
сейчас начинает говорить на славянском
language that's
языке вот и
all like squeak comment write on y Telegram
всё лайк писка комент пись на й Telegram
right now axis VN
прям зараз ось ВН
apok this is very and very important YouTube is busy with
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us through scarg Orcs in your ban and very
нас через скарг Орки в твый бан и дуже
many videos I don't show people sometimes I don't
багато видео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams so that
показуе информация про стримы тому для
we Mali tivny zvyazok is written
того щоб мы Мали тивный звязок пишиться
right now and Popik there in telegrams
прямо зараз а Попик там в телеграми
okrim video also interesting and useful
окрим видео ще теж цикава и корисна
information and we are obliged to you trimati
информация и мы повинни з вами тримати
constant operational zvyazok
постийний оперативный звязок
independently in that chi will show you the process
незалежно в того чи покаже вам проце
YouTube Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
write and
пиши а